I'm intrigued by the philosophy of
Buddhism, but I seem to disagree with
the goal. I am not afraid of suffering,
and I find that adversity is what makes
me a better person, is what drives
society to improve and gives meaning to
human life. My first impression is that
trying to simply get rid of suffering is
a sign of weakness and fear. But on the
other hand, to me, the life of a monk
seems quite difficult and far from this
notion of comfortable escapism. I'm not
so sure what to think, and your
clarification here would be appreciated.
>> Well, it certainly is a weak weakness to
try to get rid of suffering. Like, it's
the wrong path.
Um, and it's ironically what most people
are trying to do through what they think
Buddhism is. Um, and yeah, everybody
could recognize escapism is kind of
short-term benefit, long-term harm.
Um, it's it's pretty obvious. And
what you would be doing if you're
practicing rightly is actually exposing
yourself to suffering.
Not in a blind
sort of for its own sake kind of way.
Rather you would be doing things that naturally
you would be doing things that naturally
result in suffering. Not because you
want the suffering rather
restraint, renunciation,
um
taming your desires brings up suffering
because it's the opposite of what you've been
it's the opposite of what you've been
cultivating. It's a path that is thorny
because you've let it get overground.
And so
it actually you you don't have to you
don't have to be afraid that you'll be
escaping or running away from stuff if
you uh start practicing the dharma.
There's a reason why people don't do it.
It's because
everything else that they're doing is
because they're running away from this.
They're running away from
the the the wild mind that comes up when
you just go into seclusion, for example,
which is not really what you should
start with because you would probably go
mad. Like you would if you take it on
all at once. You take the average person
and you put them in a solitary
confinement, they would realize that like there
they would realize that like there
everything else was actually a a coping
mechanism for this stuff that they start
to experience when they're withdrawn
from all their distractions.
So
um
it is difficult only because like I said
you have been getting used to the
opposite. If you learn how to well if if
you you could say if you just do it long
you could say if you just do it long
enough but also it's not about just
blindly doing it and waiting for some
result. If you learn how to develop the
right values
without impatience, without trying to
force your mind to delight in the
opposite and give up everything and and
just just be um free from craving and
and all that, you realize
where the line of your input is as as
the simile of the Buddha the Buddha used
for taming a wild elephant.
You don't just like set this goal of
tomorrow I'll have it following all my
commands perfectly. You realize that
there is this
um all these habits and all these things
that have been built up because that
elephant has been just living in the
world wilderness for the last 30 years.
And so
you need to have patience to see, oh
yeah, it will have to be painful. Like
it will have to be kicking and
screaming. But then that can't last
forever. Like and certainly if you were
to quit and if you were to just give up
on the whole thing and and say, "Oh,
I'll just let the elephant go back in
the wilderness." Well,
it's not like you can actually
the simile doesn't go so far in the
sense that yeah, an elephant you just go
let it go and fine. It's not your
problem anymore. But you will have to
face the consequences of not having
tamed your mind. In fact, well, you're
already facing them really whether you
like it or not. Like you would see that
just the fact of
certain things causing you suffering or
being able to cause you suffering
already has an impact here and now.
You're already in defense stance so to
speak even if you're not actively
fighting them. And that whole
um apprehension that everybody has
towards sickness, aging, death, their
dear things being taken away, which is
happening again pretty much all day
long. um like
if they were to recognize that's that's
the the the state of defense that
they're in, they would realize, oh, if I
don't do anything about this, it's not
act it's not like I like I'm actually
avoiding all this difficulty of the
practice. I'm actually exposing myself
to a difficulty that is worse because it
has no end. That difficulty has no day.
the difficulty of uh being subject to
suffering, still being having
attachments and being liable to craving
that difficulty will never disappear on
its own. Whereas the practice, even if
it takes you 50 years to even feel like
you know what you're doing with a
dhamma, it can't last forever. Like the
difficulty can't last forever. At some
point those strong defilements that you
started with will have to get weaker and
you'll start to see oh this is actually
working and then the whole thing becomes
a bit more bearable.
So either way,
not doing the practice will always be
worse, will always bring more suffering.
Even if
um
if the suffering of the practice is more
acute, feels like it's more concentrated.
feels like it's more concentrated.
Um the suffering of not practicing might
feel like it comes and goes, but it has
no end. And that's much worse.
Maybe an extension of the simile of the
elephant could be the reason that you
brought it in to be tamed in the first
place. >> Not so much because you want to have a
>> Not so much because you want to have a
royal elephant, but
>> there was an elephant that would from
time to time come and attack your
village. >> Yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> And most of the time it wasn't.
>> But sometimes it would.
>> Yeah.
>> And the fact that it might was enough to
>> make you go out and go through.
>> Yeah. Exactly. That Yeah, that would be
a better cuz Yeah. It's not like I'm I'm
just chasing this reward for the sake of
its own pleasure. It's like if I don't
get it, I will have to face the
consequences. It's not just I didn't get
what I wanted. It's I will be actively
exposed to what I don't want.
Pain like suffering, lamentation,
sorrow, despair.
It's either you abandon those things and
develop yourself or you accept that
you're going to be exposed to them.
There's no middle ground.
What might seem like a middle ground is
managing your circumstances,
but that is not a middle ground at all.
That's really just postponing having to
face the sorrow, lamentation, and
despair. Postponing it in a way that
usually makes it painful, even more
painful when you have to face it because
you were so kind of like when you um
um
really build up this sense of
anticipation. uh for for some unpleasant thing that
uh for for some unpleasant thing that
you have to face
rather than just facing it right away,
it usually makes it worse. Usually makes
it more of a that that sense of fear
builds up even more. So the management
actually isn't the middle way between
practicing and not practicing.
It's it's still very much within the not
practicing side
and will have you facing the
consequences sooner or later because
another thing as well is
you don't know
how well your management will
how well you'll be able to maintain it
because it depends on all of these
um external conditions that could just
like you
whatever climate change,
war, anything could just compromise your
ability to keep all these pains and all
these displeasures at bay.
So
it it it requires a very very big leap
of faith
to think that you can just kind of live
your whole life kind of just keeping
your head above the water just managing
the conditions
doing what you can to prevent bad things
whenever they come up or to to um
amilarate them. takes a big big leap of
faith to to see that as a as a as a good
option. It's like hanging from a thread
perpetually. Your state is just hanging
from this thread that you have no idea
when it will break. And you would never
accept that deal if you had a choice.